Guide to the Civil War Collection 1838-1880 MS 670.14
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Civil War Collection
Bulk, 1861-1864
1838-1880
MS 670.14
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
0.834 Linear feet (2 boxes)
The Civil War Collection is an "artificial" collection of materials of unrelated provenance that have been organized together by subject matter. It includes correspondence, military and official documents, legal papers, bills and receipts, personal narratives, soldier biographies, and documents relating to slaves. Although primarily Union side, there is one folder of Confederate documents, as well as several folders of material relating to post-war memorials and publications. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Portions of the collection that have been microfilmed will be brought to the researcher in that format and can be made available by Interlibrary loan. Researchers on site may print out unlimited copies from microfilm reader-printer machines at per-exposure rates. See guidelines in Reading Room for details.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Items that include presidential signatures will be presented to researchers in duplicate form.
Arrangement note
The material in this collection has been organized by document type, and arranged chronologically within each category.
Related Materials at the New-York Historical Society
The manuscript department holds some additional papers of Thomas Jefferson Durant.
The library's extensive holdings of Civil War-related materials can be located by searching in our online
catalog
.
Scope and Contents note
The Civil War Collection is an "artificial" collection of materials that were donated by or acquired from a variety of unrelated sources but have been organized together by subject matter. The materials in this collection have been digitized and are available online to on-site researchers and to users affiliated with subscribing institutions via EBSCOhost.
The collection has been arranged into folders by document type. The majority of documents in the collection were generated by individuals or departments within the Union. Correspondence includes pre-war correspondence of figures who later participated in the Civil War; military and official correspondence; and personal correspondence of soldiers writing to relatives and loved ones. There are also several envelopes printed with soldier ballots for the presidential election of 1864.
The collection also includes a variety of Union military documents, including battle and other official reports; military orders; certificates of enlistment, discharge and pension; safe-conduct passes; court-martial papers; and requisitions, bills and receipts (including bills of lading for shipped cotton). Other official documents include oaths of allegiance to the U.S.Government and presidential pardons signed by Andrew Johnson.
There is one folder of Confederate material. It includes military correspondence (most notably, a manuscript copy of Lieutenant Hardee's letter refusing Sherman's demand to surrender Savannah), an oath of allegiance to the Confederate States of America, safe-conduct passes, reports of deserters, receipts and vouchers, and Confederate currency. There is also a folder of material relating to slaves, including an 1860 mortgage document listing all the slaves on the plantation of John Williams, receipts for slaves supplied to labor for the Confederate army, and a certificate dated August 2, 1862, freeing a slave in South Carolina.
Several folders of legal papers consist primarily of claims brought after the war for damage caused to property (including cotton) in the Confederate states by the Union army. Many of the claimants were represented by Thomas J. Durant, a New Orleans lawyer who played a prominent role in reconstruction efforts in Louisiana immediately following the war.
Other post-war materials include personal reminiscences, documents relating to Civil War memorials, and biographical sketches of soldiers solicited by Frank Moore for his Rebellion Record. Also included are several 19th century catalogs of Civil War-related material.
Durant, Thomas J., (Thomas Jefferson), 1817-1882; Moore, Frank, 1828-1904; Courts-martial and courts of inquiry; Slavery--United States; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Hospitals.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Personal Narratives.; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Prisoners and Prisons.; United States. Army--Ordnance and ordnance stores.
- Pre-war correspondence, 1838 - 1861 January (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Military and official correspondence and wrappers (includes fragments), 1861 May - 1877 July, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Personal correspondence, 1861 July - 1866 April, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Battle reports and dispatches, 1861 March - 1863 August (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Reports of Union troop strength, 1862 December - 1863 October (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Military orders, 1861 June - 1865 September, 1868 April 6 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Certificates (enlistment, discharge and pension), 1861 May - 1870 December, 1880 November (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Soldier ballot envelopes, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Inspection and morning reports, 1861 July - 1864 March, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Orders assigning 18th Army Corps Officer of the Day, 1864 August 10 - December 4 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Safe-conduct passes, 1861 May - 1865 April (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Court-martial papers, 1860 September - 1864 October (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Requisitions and returns, 1862 February - 1866, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Bills and receipts, 1861 July - 1866 May, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Hospital receipts, 1862 February - 1865 August (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Effects and case studies of deceased soldiers treated at the New York State Hospital Depot, 1863-1866; This item is a photocopy of a notebook of Ed Macgowan, hospital steward. N-YHS does not hold the original. (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Documents relating to slaves, 1860 February - 1865 June, undated (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Confederate correspondence and documents, 1861 September - 1864 June (Box 2, Folder 2)
- Oaths of allegiance and presidential pardons, 1861 September - 1864 June, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Resolutions, 1865 April 20, undated (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Legal papers and decisions, 1862 October - 1880 June, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
- Legal papers relating to cotton claims, 1867 January - 1878 October, undated (Box 2, Folder 5)
- Partial manuscript describing experiences of Mounted Rifles, undated (Box 2, Folder 6)
- Memorial and commemorative documents, 1863 September - 1868 November, undated (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Catalogs, 1863, undated (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Correspondence relating to Frank Moore's Rebellion Record, 1862 February - 1869 January, undated (Box 2, Folder 9)
- Biographical sketches for Frank Moore's Rebellion Record (A-K), undated (Box 2, Folder 10)
- Biographical sketches for Frank Moore's Rebellion Record (L-Z), undated (Box 2, Folder 11)